It's been an interesting morning from a
volatility regime and I want to take you
through it. It's one of the few moments
where you'll get to see how the S&Ps
compared to its subcomponents. And we
can break that down by taking a look at
the S&P, the Dow, and the NASDAQ and
comparing the volatility across the
board and then the individual sectors as
well. Now, let's start with the S&P 500.
The S&P's on its scalper volatility box
models and we've just been chopping
around sideways. We have yet to hit
either side entry lines. So, if you
looked at just the S&P, you would think
that today is a fairly calm and muted
volatility day. However, as soon as you
come into the Dow, that vision, that
idea should be blurred. The Dow just
obliterated through its scalper
volatility box models. We broke right
through the clouds and inside of the
Dow, you had to adapt outside of the
scalper, the aggressive, the doomsday
aggressive, the conservative, and
finally, it's the doomsday conservative
models that held. So, at least we know
now that the volatility inside of the
Dow is much higher than inside of the
S&P 500. Another thing that's
interesting is the Dow breached its
doomsday conservative models on
strength. You can see this rally here.
Contrast that with the NASDAQ. The
NASDAQ also breached its doomsday
conservative models, but it did that on
weakness. So, in terms of strength, we
can see that the Dow has strength. The
NASDAQ very clear weakness. Both enough
weakness and enough strength to take
them to their most conservative
volatility box models. Meanwhile, you
have the S&P, which is essentially
getting stretched thin from both ways.
the Dow pulling it up, the NASDAQ
pulling it down, and as of right now,
you can see that the NASDAQ is winning a
little bit more in terms of which the
chart looks more similar to. Now, you
might be wondering, well, which sectors
are contributing to this volatility? So
for that we could load in our spy
sectors here and we could take a look at
each of these sectors but now with our
hourly volatility box models for stocks
and ETFs. This now tells us the picture
under the subcomponents of the
individual index markets. So you take a
look at XLF for example. XLF very
clearly contributing to that strength
that we see inside of the Dow. You take
a look at XLI, you see similar strength
in XLI, but not as much as we saw inside
of XLF. A little bit less. And if
anything, XLI is currently triggering a
bearish setup here. Looking for a short
side entry. XLB, take a look at XLB. You
see similar volatility to what you saw
in XLI. So very clearly for the Dow,
it's XLF that is the major component,
the major contribution for why we had
the rally. We keep going down the index
markets and you can take a look to see
which sectors are a little bit more
volatile. XLK, great example of the
volatility that's contributing to the
NASDAQ volatility. However, XLK much
more tradable compared to the NASDAQ
which is on its doomsday conservative
models. You take a look at XLC and just
like the ES futures, you would almost
think what volatility, huh? Same thing
with XLP. Consumer staples have
absolutely no volatility so far to start
off the day. Take a look at energy. Same
idea. XLV, a little bit more volatility.
In fact, very similar to what we saw
inside of XLF. So now you know the two
sectors very clearly contributing to the
strength in the Dow. XLF, XLV. These are
the two sectors that are leading to the
rally that we saw. And in terms of the
sell-off, we saw XLK was the one market
in which we broke outside of our models.
So the NASDAQ seems to have a better
grip on right now. Tech a little bit
more tradable compared to what we're
seeing inside of XLF and XLV. Okay. So
at this point we've understood the
volatility with the index markets. We
looked at ES YM and NQ. We understand ES
least volatile YM NQ both on their
doomsday conservative models. YM for the
bullish side or rather rallying and NQ
off of more bearish activity. We also
took a look at sectors and we understood
XLV, XLF are contributing to the rally,
XLK to the decline. So those are the
sectors that stand out. Now let's take a
look at all of this information and try
and actually find some trades. I've
loaded in our stock volatility box
scanner here and we're going to look at
the S&P 100 first. Inside of the S&P
100, take a look at how many short
setups versus long setups. So, a lot of
these setups right now are shortside
setups, meaning that there's strength in
them and we're looking to fade the
strength. I'd like to see which are the
long side setups where we have
opportunities. And Google stands out. We
just talked about how tech is offering
us some opportunities. Another one,
Target. And then we have Google again,
but this time off of their hourly
models. You'll see this batch is hourly.
This batch of Google is their daily
models being breached. The daily models
have a better score. So that's the one
I'm going to be using. And in both
cases, we can see we have the stage of
acceleration. So now I can come back in
to let's use Google or go. If we take a
look at the class C shares, we can see
that Google seems to be building some
sort of a base here. This is what it
looks like on the hourly models. And now
if I load in the daily models, we can
see that Google has bounced straight
into our daily volatility box models.
And so far, we've bounced up from there.
I'd like to see if we can get a slightly
deeper entry if possible. Mostly because
we know that today is a volatile day and
Google is on my radar looking for a
longside entry if we can come back
inside of the clouds and maybe even
break below this low. I'd like an entry
closer to the 285 28550 mark closer to
the outer edge of the models which if we
come into our daily time frame chart
excuse me daily time frame chart we can
see we're a bit extended from the market
pulse. So, I'd like to get a little bit
greedier.
Markets now closed and I thought I'd do
a quick recap of what happened when we
were looking at Google. This is where
Google was trading. We were trading
sideways close to the first target line.
If you remember, we wanted our entry
near 285 to 28550
and Google ended up falling directly
there. I used the dip below 285 to start
to build up my position. Here's the
tracking price for Thinker Swim, 284.82.
And that still was not the best price
for the day. We fell a little bit more
beyond that as well. In terms of the
upper target, I was looking for 288.09.
We fell a little bit shy of that and I
closed out the position in the final few
seconds really before the market closed.
So there was the Google trade. If I
recap where this all started, we started
with the index markets looking at the
S&P 500 first. The S&P very clearly
signaled to us that we didn't have a lot
of volatility.
What's interesting is when we started to
look at the other counterparts with the
Dow and the NASDAQ, we saw a much
different story. The NASDAQ told us that
there's a lot of volatility. In fact, we
breached our doomsday conservative
models and we were looking for longside
setups here. Inside of the Dow, it was
the opposite. The Dow, we breached the
upper models and we were looking for
short side setups. And take a look what
ends up happening for the rest of the
day. Ends up being the high for the Dow
and short side setups were the better
setups to be looking at here. We had
identified two sectors XLF and XLV. XLF
was the better short side setup. I'll
load in the hourly models. And we can
see how the high that we looked at early
in the morning when we were evaluating
was the high that ended up holding for
the rest of the day inside of XLV. XLV
continued to keep drifting up higher,
not with as much strength as we saw in
the morning, but we did see XLV drift up
all the way into our daily volatility
box models. So, a lot more strength in
XLV versus XLF. And in terms of our uh
other sector for the longside sector, we
were looking at XLK, which is where we
found Google. And XLK ended up holding
really nicely from where we were looking
at it. It mirrored the Google trade that
we were looking at, which again was a
handful of the long side setups. We had
Google, we had Target, uh, when we were
looking at the scanner, and Google was
the one that we ended up focusing in on,
which ended up playing out fairly
nicely. I hope you found this video
helpful in understanding how to use both
the futures and the stock volatility box
models to piece together a complete
volatility picture. Whether you're an
ETF trader, you trade sectors, or you
trade futures or individual stocks,
you'll find that the volatility box
models help you understand where there's
volatility opportunities. And then you
can use things like the scanner to
pinpoint exactly when and where these
setups are triggering. Hope you found
this video helpful. Take care, everyone.
Good luck trading, and be sure to check
out some of our recent videos if you'd
like to learn more about volatility
trading.
>> [music]